Good morning, today's דף daf officially is ל"ב. Lamed Bais. We pick
up on the top of ל"א עמוד ב', Lamed Aleph Amud Bais,
where we're in the middle of a lot of core parameters of
אבידה. aveida. First of all, we've been dealing with some exceptions to
the rule, which the גמרא Gemara had a דרשה drasha of והתעלמת
מהם: ve-hisalamta mei-hem: sometimes you're supposed to ignore, to mention three things,
and we're actually going to see all of those three things. We've
seen one of them come up in the coming משניות. mishnayos. So
one of them is: it's beneath your dignity to return it, and
that's an interesting idea—that beyond the idea that you protect your own
property before somebody else's, here's even protecting your dignity before somebody else's
property. The other two things that we learned from that is not
to violate another הלכה, halacha, like go into a cemetery if you're
a כהן—that's kohen coming up in a משנה—and mishna
the really first principle I said, which is: don't return it if
it's going to come to a greater loss to yourself in the
process of returning it. That was even mentioned in our משנה mishna
about how much you can be reimbursed for, and sometimes if you
can't afford it, you actually don't have to return it. So that
was one interesting set of exceptions that we dealt with. The other
interesting thing that came up in the גמרא Gemara just to mention
was the idea that it applies to possibly אבידת קרקע, aveidat karka,
stopping a land from being damaged, which is not only conceptually a
shift from returning a piece of property to an immovable object to
an immovable piece of property, but also the idea of preventing loss
and not only returning an object to its owner—more abstracting it. And
that's very important because then the גמרא Gemara dealt with the last
thing we saw yesterday was the idea that you have to return
it, even a hundred times, and the משנה mishna makes it sound
like that's from the double language of השב תשיבם, hashev teshivem, but
רבא Rava basically said, "No, no, no, the word השב hashev itself
means as many times as necessary, and the doubling is come to
expanding the scope of things that you have to return." And then
the גמרא Gemara did that for a couple of different מצוות—that mitzvot
the doubling of the language doesn't mean multiple times, that you get
from the first word; the doubling of the language expands the scope
of the scenarios. But important for this, for these types of collections
of things that we're teaching
here, in terms of the basic parameters, is the idea that at
the end of that the גמרא Gemara said, we sort of take
a step back and said, "Why does the תורה Torah have to
tell me both אבידה aveida and פריקה וטעינה?" perika u-ti'ina? Because now
we're sort of abstracting that basically what it means is protect somebody's
property, and if אבידה aveida doesn't just mean return a lost object,
but prevent a property from damage, then why do I need a
separate מצוה mitzvah about unloading and reloading up the animal? So part
of that might have to be the מצוה mitzvah of the reloading
of the animal—that's not just protecting against
damage—but אלא, ella, even in terms of the other, the unloading, the
גמרא Gemara pointed out that there are differences. In the case of
the unloading of the animal, there's maybe more of an obligation because
of צער בעלי חיים—something tza'ar ba'alei chayim which we'll hopefully get to
see today—and in terms of the אבידה, aveida, there's more of an
obligation because the owner isn't around. So these different פסוקים psukim are
telling me the scope of my obligation of protecting people's property in
the various scenarios. So it's really very interesting that we're now dealing
at a more abstract level, protecting somebody's property, but also exemptions to
it when protecting my own property or my own dignity actually comes
first. Okay, so now we pick up at the top of ל"א
עמוד ב', Lamed Aleph Amud Bais, where we're going to continue going
through these double
languages, השב תשיבם hashev teshivem etc., and see what the doubling comes
to teach here. Okay, so we'll do this—so we're just going to
go through a couple of things not really related to אבידה. aveida.
Top of ל"א עמוד ב', Lamed Aleph Amud Bais, three lines from
the top: מות יומת המכה. mos yumat ha-makeh. The murderer shall be
certainly put to death. So you can't say even מאה פעמים; me'ah
pe'amim;
that wouldn't work here. So the גמרא Gemara says, אין לי אלא
במיתה הכתובה
בו—I ein li ella be-misah ha-ksuvah bo only know that if you
can give him the proper execution for the murderer, like by the
sword. מנין שאם אי אתה יכול להמיתו במיתה הכתובה בו שאתה רשאי
להמיתו בכל מיתה שאתה יכול
להמיתו—how minayin she-im ee atah yachol le-hamito be-misah ha-ksuvah bo she-atah rashai
le-hamito be-chol misah she-atah yachol le-hamito do I know if you can't
do that execution, you have the license to do any form of
execution? So the scenario would be that somebody has already had the
death sentence passed on them, and then they manage to stage a
jailbreak, and there they are, they're running away, and the only way
that you can stop the guy is by shooting him. So how
do you know that you are entitled—that that is a like some
type of a licensed form of
execution? So this is not while the trial is going on, this
is not when somebody is suspected. This is also not the law
of somebody who actually is in the process of trying to attempt
to murder somebody; that's a different הלכה. halacha. This is when somebody
has had a גמר דין gmar din that they have to be
put to death, and for some reason the only way you are
going to be able to do this is by some other form
of execution. How do you know you have the license to do
that? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, the verse teaches: מות יומת מכל מקום,
mos yumat mi-kol makom, in however you have to put him to
death. Okay, now הכה תכה. hakei takeh. Now this is about
smiting the עיר הנדחת, ir nidachas, the worshippers of the עיר הנדחת.
ir nidachas. אין לי אלא בהכאה הכתובה בו ein li ela behaka'ah
haketuva bo
I only know that it's through again the Torah says by the
עיר הנדחת ir hanidachat לפי חרב lefi charev by the sword. מנין
שאם אי אתה יכול להמיתם בהכאה הכתובה בהן minayin she-im i ata
yakhol lehamitam behaka'ah haketuva bahen
how do I know if you're not going to be able to
implement that שאתה רשאי להכותם בכל הכאה שאתה יכול she-ata rashai lehakotam
bekhol haka'ah she-ata yakhol that you can execute them in whatever means
you find possible תלמוד לומר הכה תכה מכל מקום talmud lomar hakeh
takeh mikol makom however you have to however it must be done.
השב תשיב hashev tashiv
okay this is now not השבת אבידה hashavat aveidah but returning the
collateral if somebody a poor person gives a collateral then you'll hold
on to it in the day and you return it in the
night or you hold on to it at night and return it
in the day depending on whether he whether he needs it at
night or needs it at the day and so what is the
double language of you shall surely returning? אין לי אלא שמשכנו ברשות
בית דין ein li ela she-mashkeno birshut beit din
I only know that the Torah's talking about when you took the
collateral through the agency of the court you had you sent in
a court officer to seize collateral from this guy okay משכנו שלא
ברשות בית דין mashkeno she-lo birshut beit din if you didn't do
it through the court you did it by yourself מנין minayin how
do I know then? Which is a question because you might think
if you that sounds like a little bit like you were acting
a little illegally so all the more that you have an obligation
to return it but maybe it also means maybe it was done
through a private agreement maybe he willingly gave you the collateral so
maybe if it was a private agreement and it wasn't a forceful
one through the court maybe you shouldn't have the same obligation to
return it
תלמוד לומר השב תשיב מכל מקום talmud lomar hashev tashiv mikol makom
under all circumstances. Okay אם חבל תחבל שלמת רעך im chavol tachbol
salmat re'akha this is you know this is the same type of
the context of returning the collateral if you shall take as collateral
so what's this double language? why do you need both of them
to begin with? what? well let's take a look. מה? ma what
do you mean double language? yeah so so then we're going to
ask that why do you need both of them to begin with?
ah well because one is כסות יום ksut yom
and one is כסות לילה. ksut laila. אין לי אלא שמשכנו ברשות
ein li ela she-mashkeno birshut I only know if you took it
with permission משכנו שלא ברשות מנין mashkeno she-lo birshut minayin so this
is not just שלא ברשות בית דין she-lo birshut beit din this
is not that you had a private agreement this is just you
burst broke into his house and took something as collateral so how
do I know? Now of course that's a big what do you
mean how do I know? if anything I would like to know
how do you know you get to keep it at all let
alone how do you know that you get have to return it
on a daily basis. So I'm not exactly sure why this required
a חידוש chiddush here but maybe that's what it means actually how
do I know maybe you are allowed to keep it maybe we're
talking about that we're not yet talking about the מצוה mitzvah to
return. Anyway תלמוד לומר חבל תחבל מכל מקום. talmud lomar chavol tachbol
mikol makom. והני תרי קראי למה לי? ve-hani terei krayei lama li?
So that's Michael's question because one of them is in שמות כ"ה
Shemot Chaf-He and the other is שמות כ"ד Shemot Chaf-Dalet why do
I need two פסוקים psukim about returning collateral? So חד לכסות יום
וחד לכסות לילה chad likhsut yom ve-chad likhsut laila one to tell
me if you take a day garment that you have to return
it during the day and one if you take a night garment
you have to return it at night. Wouldn't that be obvious? I
don't know but yes but it's a different גמרא Gemara not for
us. פתוח תפתח patoach tiftach okay now
this is if somebody asks for a loan right oh right because
of יום טוב Yom Tov if somebody asks for a loan it
says you shall surely open your hand פתוח תפתח את ידך לו
והעבט תעביטנו די מחסורו אשר יחסר לו patoach tiftach et yadekha lo
ve-ha'aveit ta'avitenu dei machsoro asher yikhsar lo and you should loan him
the money as much as he needs. Now the פסוקים psukim are
talking about a loan of money but classically חז"ל Chazal some sort
of like bracket some aspects of that פסוק pasuk and their primary
reader the פסוק pasuk seems to be give him money like what
we call צדקה. tzedakah. They also understand that there is a מצוה
mitzvah to loan and there's a whole discussion when should you be
loaning and when should you be giving but what you have to
know in this גמרא Gemara here is that initially we're sort of
looking at this פסוק pasuk more as it's about giving money as
צדקה tzedakah but we'll also get to the idea of loaning money.
Okay אין לי אלא לעני עירך ein li ela le-ani irkha so
what's the double language of פתוח תפתח? patoach tiftach? I only know
that you have to do it you know if it's in your
city because I think some of the פסוקים psukim say you know
בשעריך bish'arekha or something עני עיר אחרת מנין ani ir acheret minayin
how do I know then? Which is a question because you might
think if you that sounds like a little bit like you were
acting a little illegal so all the more that you have an
obligation but maybe it also means maybe it was done through a
private agreement maybe he willingly gave you the collateral so maybe if
it was a private agreement and it wasn't a forceful one through
the court maybe you shouldn't have the same obligation to return it.
תלמוד לומר פתוח תפתח talmud lomar patoach tiftach you shall surely open
your hand so whether it's from your city or another one and
as we know there's a famous דרשה drasha that while those of
your town take precedence here the point is that at least the
obligation does extend beyond that. העבט תעביטנו ha'aveit ta'avitenu what?
We're getting to. אין לי אלא מתנה מרובה ein li ela matana
meruba now I only know if it's a big one if it's
a big gift מתנה מועטת מנין matana mu'atet minayin now
because it says די מחסורו dei machsoro as much as he lacks
so maybe you'll say well if I can't give him everything that
he lacks maybe I don't have an obligation to give him a
dollar okay I mean I'm sure he'd appreciate it but how do
I know that I have an obligation? Maybe my obligation is really
to get him back on his feet and maybe for you know
or to fully give him what he needs he needs a full
meal giving him like an apple or a grape maybe there's no
מצוה mitzvah in that תלמוד לומר נתון תתן talmud lomar naton titein
give him regardless you know even the smallest amount if you can't
give him everything he needs. מכל מקום. mikol makom.
העניק תעניק לו ha'aneik ta'anik lo this is a different this is
also about giving but different about giving the the slave that worked
for you when you send him free in the seventh year you
shall surely load him up so אין לי אלא שנתברך הבית בגללו
ein li ela she-nitbarekh habayit biglalo because the end of the פסוק
pasuk says you know because because you know because he. Because of
all the good that he did you, כי משנה שכר שכיר עבדך
שש שנים וברכך ה' אלקיך, ki mishneh sechar sachir avadcha shesh shanim
u-veirach'cha Hashem Elokecha,
God blessed you as a result, maybe God didn't bless you, maybe
ever since he's been working for me he's been I have not
been so successful in business. אין לי אלא נתברך הבית בגללו מעניקין
לו, לא נתברך הבית בגללו מנין? ein li ela nitbarech habayis biglalo
ma'anikin lo, lo nitbarech habayis biglalo minayin? How do I know even
if I was not successful I have an obligation to give him,
you know, to load him up? תלמוד לומר הענק תעניק מכל מקום.
Talmud lomar ha'anek ta'anik mikal makom. This is like pushing time around
bonus season.
Is it good? Yeah, exactly.
All these big investment banks that the people get these huge bonuses
even if the company lost money. ורבי אלעזר בן עזריה דאמר נתברך
הבית בגללו מעניקין לו, לא נתברך הבית בגללו אין מעניקין לו. v'Rabbi
Elazar ben Azarya d'amar nitbarech habayis biglalo ma'anikin lo, lo nitbarech habayis
biglalo ein ma'anikin lo. How about Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya that says
no, actually you don't have to give him all these gifts if
the house, if you were not successful. So הענק תעניק למה לי?
ha'anek ta'anik lama li? So
what's the double language of הענק תעניק לו? ha'anek ta'anik lo? So
here the גמרא Gemara says דברה תורה כלשון בני אדם. dibra Torah
k'lishon bnei adam.
Fine,
sometimes it doesn't mean anything, sometimes it's just the way of speaking
that you use a double language. Of course that leads תוספות Tosafot
to a whole big discussion about how do you know when it's
דברה תורה כלשון בני אדם dibra Torah k'lishon bnei adam and when
do you know when it's not. So תוספות Tosafot basically points out,
okay, we assume that it's coming to teach you something and to
broaden the scope, but if other פסוקים psukim indicate that there's no
good way to broaden the scope, then we'll say דברה תורה כלשון
בני אדם. dibra Torah k'lishon bnei adam. Okay, העבט תעביטנו, ha'aveit ta'avitenu,
now this is going back to the פסוקים. psukim. It's funny that
the גמרא Gemara sort of shifted gears, but maybe it's going between
gifts and loans. So going back to the earlier פסוק pasuk which
says that you know if a poor person asks you for money,
so before we were more reading it through the lens of a
gift of צדקה, tzedaka, now we're going back to those פסוקים psukim
and here the words of העבט תעביטנו ha'aveit ta'avitenu are clearly words
of a loan because it's mean, the word means collateral, so it's
a word, the verb means to give a loan. So going back
to those פסוקים psukim about giving money, but now looking at the
fact that they're really talking about loans, so what are we going
to learn out from that double language
העבט תעביטנו? ha'aveit ta'avitenu? אין לי אלא שאין לו ואינו רוצה להתפרנס.
ein li ela she-ein lo v'eino rotze l'hitparnes. I only know you're
obligated to give a loan if a person does not have, you
know, their own money, and they don't want to accept the gift.
So they don't have their own money to support themselves, they refuse
to accept the gift, then you give a loan, which is interesting,
which means if he's willing to accept the gift, it would be
better to give a gift than to give a loan, which is,
it's a debate, it's a debate. Okay, it's a very fascinating גמרא
Gemara that's not ours in כתובות Ketubot that discusses those priorities. But
the more point here is not that he's refusing a gift, but
that he has no money of his own. So I only know
there's an obligation to give a loan if he has no money
of his own. Okay, אמר רחמנא תן לו דרך הלואה. amar Rachmana
ten lo derech halva'ah.
So then, okay, if he has no money of his own and
he refuses a gift, give him a loan. Fine. יש לו ואינו
רוצה להתפרנס מנין? yesh lo v'eino rotze l'hitparnes minayin?
Now let's say he's got money, but he's got money but he
refuses to go into his money, like he basically, I don't know,
he's got a house, okay, but he's but he would rather, you
know, there are people called like house poor, okay. House rich and
asset poor. Oh, that's good, house rich and asset poor. Okay, fine.
So whatever it is, okay, whatever it is, he's got some stuff.
Okay, here's a guy, whatever, he's got his 67 Corvette, I don't
even know if that's the right year for a classic Corvette, okay,
which is worth a hundred thousand dollars and he will not part
for it, part with it, for anything, okay, but he has no
money. So basically here he is, he's living on like pasta every
day and sleeping in the street so he does not have to
give, sell his 67 Corvette, but and he refuses to take money,
but he will take a loan. Do you have an obligation to
loan this guy money or can you say he's an idiot, let
him sell his Corvette? Okay. So how do you know somebody that
has money but refuses to use it, okay, and he doesn't refuse,
he refuses to take a gift, how do you know even that
person you have a מצוה mitzvah to lend him money? Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says יש לו ואינו רוצה להתפרנס מנין תלמוד לומר
תעביטנו מכל מקום, yesh lo v'eino rotze l'hitparnes minayin, Talmud lomar ta'avitenu
mikal makom, regardless. So some people have whatever שטיקים shticks that they
have, but that doesn't mean that you can ignore your obligation to
him. You lend him the money, okay. And anyway, you know, so
okay, fine. So but isn't that really in a case where he
actually had, where it's not liquid? But let's say he really has
like this big flush bank account and he just doesn't want to
go into it. Yeah. Do you really have to support? Yeah, I
don't know, that's a harder question. Yeah, I don't know. I was
trying to give it a place where it's a little more reasonable.
No, I know, I understand. Okay. So I don't know, I mean
that's it does sound like that, it does sound. I mean רש"י
Rashi says יש לו ואינו רוצה להתפרנס משלו אלא משלך, yesh lo
v'eino rotze l'hitparnes mishalo ela mishalcha, right? You know, so that is
very strange, right? So then maybe someone who's really poor that you
can't give as much to because this guy is just, I understand.
So anyway, so at least there's an opposing position here of רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon דאמר d'amar יש לו ואינו רוצה להתפרנס אין נזקקין
לו. yesh lo v'eino rotze l'hitparnes ein nizkakin lo. Somebody who actually
has money, you don't have any obligation to that person. תעביטנו למה
לי? ta'avitenu lama li? So what's the double language? So דברה תורה
כלשון בני אדם. dibra Torah k'lishon bnei adam. Right, because that's because
people need a home. I understand, which is why I was giving
a case. Right, so keeping a house is more obvious. You need
a place to sleep. I was trying to give a case where
you really, you know, you could sell your Corvette. You don't need
your classic Corvette. And Michael was saying correctly that the פשט *pshat*
of the סוגיא *sugya* is even when you actually have a big
bank account, you just don't want to draw on those funds. Yes.
Yes, it works both ways. In Florida and Texas, people who used
to be millionaires will buy a mansion because when they go bankrupt,
then their assets are protected. The mansion is protected. It can be.
Right. Right. Of course. Alright. We left off... yes. You said there
was a גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in כתובות *Kethubot* that disagrees with this
in terms of the priority of צדקה *tzedakah*? Not disagrees, it deals
with a range of opinions. Yeah. Okay, so you take a look
here. It's cross-referenced. Okay. כתובות סז ע״ב *Kethubot samech-zayin amud bet*. So
if you're interested in that, that's a fascinating גמרא Gemara *Gemara* about
different priorities of loans versus צדקה *tzedakah*. What? Yeah. Okay. Now, היה
מבטל מן הסלע לא יאמר לו תן לי סלע אלא ela, נותן
לו שכר כפועל *Haya mivatel min haselah lo yomar lo ten li
selah ela noten lo s'char k'poel*. So now we get to the
idea that you are entitled to some type of a, you know,
of a reimbursement, as Eugene said nicely yesterday, sort of like a
jury duty reimbursement. You're not going to get paid what your law
firm would pay you. You'll get paid for some certain flat fee.
So what is that fee you are being paid for in returning
the אבידה aveida. *aveida*? Because you can't be actually paid for the
מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*, but you can be paid for the time you
took off. What's that called? Opportunity cost. It's not really opportunity cost,
because it's not the money you lost. It's just your time. So
let's see how the גמרא Gemara? *Gemara* figures it out. Okay? So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. נותן לו כשכר כפועל בטל
*Noten lo ke-schar ke-poel batel*. מאי כפועל בטל *Mai ke-poel batel*? What's
like a worker who is not doing anything? What does that mean?
How do you figure it out? Or what's the idea? אמר אביי
כפועל בטל של אותה מלאכה דבטל מינה *Amar Abaye ke-poel batel shel
oto melacha de-batel mineih*. Like a פועל *poel*, like a worker who
is not doing the labor that he is not doing. So what
does that mean? So רש״י *Rashi*, it's very vague. So רש״י *Rashi*
says what it basically means is what I told you yesterday, which
is, okay, you are, let's not do the case of a lawyer,
you work in a quarry, you know, like a whatever, mining granite
or whatever. I'm thinking about Fred Flintstone, that's my view of a
quarry. Okay? So you do this hard labor and you earn twenty
dollars an hour. Okay? How much would you accept to take an
hour off of work and to just return a lost object? So
on the one hand, you know, you're not earning your twenty dollars.
On the other hand, it's a lot easier. It's just some going
door to
door and knocking on some doors or whatever. It gives you a
nice break. So maybe I would take, you know, so maybe in
that
case, I would take five bucks in order to do that, right?
Because, you know, I would because I would take a lot less
money in order to not have to work so hard. Okay? I
wouldn't take nothing because I can't afford to take nothing or whatever,
but anyway I would take five dollars in order to stop my
work, in order to give myself a break from my work for
that hour. Okay? So that's what you basically pay this guy. You
pay him a convenience fee? No, no, no. That's the standard. The
standard. So you just offer him this from the very beginning? Oh
let me reimburse you for your time?
Yeah, yeah, from the very beginning he has to be reimbursed for
his time. But his time is not the time that is lost
in what he could have earned by working hard. The time is
sort of, you know, what he would have taken. If you look
at רש״י *Rashi*, let's read רש״י *Rashi*. כמה אדם רוצה ליטול לפחות
משכרו לבטל ממלאכה זו כבדה שיושב בה לעשות במלאכה קלה כזו הכל
לפי כובד המלאכה וריבוי השכר. יש מלאכה שטרחה קל ושכר רב או
חילופו *Kama adam rotzeh litol lifchot mi-scharo levatel mi-melacha zu kveida she-yoshev
bah la'asot bi-melacha kala ka-zo hakol lefi koved ha-melacha ve-ribui ha-schar. Yesh
melacha she-tarchah kal ve-schar rav o chilufo*. Okay? Now the point is,
so if you're doing working in a quarry for twenty dollars an
hour, you might be happy to take off an hour, you give
me ten bucks to, ten bucks will be worth it for me
to take off an hour. Five bucks would be worth it for
me to take off an hour. Maybe not ten hours, I can't
afford that, but maybe for one hour, yes. Okay? But if I'm
a lawyer and I'm making three hundred dollars an hour, and I
have to, you have to ask me to return an אבידה aveida
*aveida*, first of all, doing returning an אבידה aveida *aveida* might be
less fun, more work for me than whatever, and I wouldn't take
anything under three hundred dollars to stop doing my work. Right? Or
if as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to say or as
the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* says, if I need the money, I would
love to be able to take an hour off for five bucks,
but I need to put food on the table. Okay? So those
are cases in which you have to make this stipulation with the
בית דין beit din, *Beit Din*, because, so, you know, in one
case פועל בטל *poel batel* actually is very high to your original
salary because your original salary is not, because maybe you don't actually,
it's not so much work for you, you know, in terms of
the amount you're making, so even to take off, you know, why
would you take a lot of money to take off? Why would
you take money to take off? So even פועל בטל *poel batel*
might be very high. There's another case where, where פועל בטל *poel
batel* in theory would be lower if it, but you don't, but
you can't afford it. Okay? And those are the types of cases
where you're going to get paid, where you can stipulate to get
paid essentially the money you're losing. So let's take a look. אם
יש שם בית דין מתנה בפניהם Im yesh sham beit din matneh
bifneihem, *Im yesh sham beit din matneh bifneihem*. So if there was
a court then you stipulate with them. So it
says... that you're going to return it on the condition that you
get reimbursed for the money you're losing. Okay.
Wait a minute. I mean you can do that, you can get
around it like you said a minute ago. Right. Right, exactly. Right.
Right, exactly. Okay. So you have all these stories in גמרא Gemara.
and גמרא Gemara about people, Rabbis who were working, they didn't even
like say hello to somebody because they're in the middle of some
kind of work. So someone like that, expects also to like... well
that's usually built into the contract that if something like this happens
it's understood that your employer will let you take off. You know
what, that's an excellent point that we're not discussing here, right, which
is like what are your obligations to your
employer? You know, I mean if I found this during and I'm
returning it on a, you know, on a day that I'm not
working, so then why do I have פועל בטלה? Poel Batala? And
if I... and if I mean you could be self-employed, but you
know, which could be the easier scenario here. But if you have
an employer, you know, it's all very nice that you're willing to
take off and you're willing to take this sort of jury-duty type
of wages, but why is that fair, you know, why does your
employer have to allow you to do that? That's a very good
point. That is a really good point. I have to get back
to him on that. Like, is the employer entitled to say the
same way you're basically entitled to say my protecting my, you know,
financial well-being comes before protecting somebody else's financial well-being, right, maybe the
employer's entitled to say like, you know, I need you to do
this work, and if you're not here doing this work, then I'm
going to have to find somebody else to work, I'm going to
have a loss... so you know, my need essentially prevents you from
taking off this time. That's a really good question. I'm going to
look to see if I can find something on that. I love
you but he pays me. Exactly. That is a really good question.
So I'm going to get back to you on that. Jury duty
is built into law. A person is required to... Right, exactly. Exactly.
That's a state law. Exactly. Right. Jury duty is a good analogy
to that. Your employer can't say no. But yeah, they don't have
to pay though. Although mine
does. Right. Interesting. Alright, anyway, it's a really good question. I'm going
to try to see if I can find something on that. אם
יש שם בית דין מתנה בפניהם, Im yesh sham beit din matneh
bifneihem. if there's a court then you stipulate with them. Listen, I'm
only going to return this if I can get my full salary
because I cannot give up my normal salary. So איסור וספרא Issur
v'Safra and then it says and then if presumably I don't know
if they just give you a stamp, a, you know like a
blanket stamp of approval or if they assess that it's worth it
for, you know, putting themselves in the position of the loser of
the object and assess that it's worth it and then they approve
it. You know, they approve it for X amount of hours but
not for more. Like it's an interesting question what role they play.
Okay. Anyway, איסור וספרא עבדי עיסקא בהדי הדדי, Issur v'Safra avdi iska
bahadi hadadei, Issur and Safra
were in business together. אזל ספרא Azal Safra and presumably being in
business together means that they bought some stuff, you know, they bought
all of these DVDs, I'm no longer dealing with VCRs, okay, and
then they're going to sell the DVDs and they have 2,000 boxes
of DVDs, okay, and they each contributed equal amount of money. אזל
ספרא פליג בלא דעתא
דאיסור. Azal Safra palig b'lo da'ata d'Issur. Issur wasn't around, Safra maybe
decided he was going to go try selling them somewhere else, he'd
be more successful, whatever. Anyway, whatever he decided, and he basically said
I'm going to take half of the DVDs, a thousand of them,
and I'm splitting the partnership. Okay, and he did it unilaterally, the
other guy wasn't around. Okay, but he did and he did it
באפי בי תרי, b'appei bei trei, two people were there, two witnesses,
so that it should be clear that it was all up above
board, he only took exactly half, and so
on. אתא לקמיה דרבה בר רב הונא. Ata l'kammei d'Rabba bar Rav
Huna. He went... it came in front of Rabba bar Rav Huna.
אמר ליה זיל אייתי תלתא דפלגת קמייהו. Amar lei zil ayiti tlata
d'palgat kammaihu. No, two is not enough to make for a legal
division if you're doing it unilaterally. You'd have to have been three.
So either bring three people that you did it before them, that
it was a בית דין, beit din. או אינמי o inami תרי
מיגו תלתא, trei migo tlata, or you don't have to have produced
all three, you can produce two from the three but they'll testify
to the fact that they were part of a בית דין. beit
din או אינמי o inami it doesn't even have to be the
בית דין beit din. that's testifying, תרי סהדי, trei sahadi, let there
be two witnesses, but they have to testify to the fact דפלגת
באפי תלתא, d'palgat b'appei tlata, that you did it in front of
a בית דין. beit din You need a בית דין beit din?
to validate a unilateral transaction like that, the same way in our
משנה. Mishnah, אמר ליה מנלך הא, Amar lei menalach ha, where you
get this idea that there needs to be a בית דין? beit
din אמר ליה דתנן, Amar lei detnan, our משנה, Mishna. אם יש
שם בית דין beit din מתנה בפניהם. That was a unilateral type
of an arrangement without the presence of the other party, so you
need the בית דין beit din to represent the interest of the
other party and to say that it's okay. Makes a lot of
sense. Okay. אמר ליה מי דמי, Amar lei mi dami, he said
how can you compare
them? התם דמפיק ממונא מהאי ומותיב להאי Hatam d'mappik mammona mehai u-mativ
lehai בעינן בית דין, ba'inan beit din, right, because what am I
going to do? I'm going to return this lost object and I'm
going to say to the guy here, you owe me a hundred
dollars an hour for my returning of this lost object. And he's
going to say are you kidding? I would never do that. So
there when we're going to ask him to pay out money, you
need a בית דין beis din. to represent his side and essentially
agree for him. Whether in the end he likes it or not,
they're going to have to make that judgment call, and obviously it's
going to be limited to the cost of the object. That's when
you need a בית דין beis din when you're going to be
asking that other side to pay out money. Okay. ומותיב להאי בעינן
בית דין אבל הכא דידי קא שקיל גילויי מלתא בעלמא הוא. u-mativ
lehai ba'inan beit din aval hacha didi ka-shakil gillui miltha b'alma hu.
Here, I was just taking my own property. I wasn't taking something
away from him, we were partners. in this, right? It was not
an abstract sense of a corporation. It was a partnership. So I
literally owned half of the object. So you could say, well, I
don't know which DVD you own, which one thousand out of the
two thousand you owned. Fine, but that's like a type of a
ברירה. breira. At the end of the day, I'll take a thousand
and then we'll decide those were my thousand. But we're not, I'm
not taking money away from him. I'm just taking the stuff which
we're going to say was mine all along. So גילויי מילתא בעלמא
הוא, giluya milsa b'alma hu, בי תרי סגיא ליה, bei trei sagi
lei, two should be enough. תא שמע: Ta shema: דתנן: d'tnan: אלמנה
מוכרת שלא בפני בית דין. almanah mocheres shelo bifnei beis din. A
widow can sell property from the estate not in the presence of
a בית דין. beis din Why? Because she has a lien on
it and she has a right to it. So when you're taking
something that you fundamentally have a right to, it has to be
above board, you need to make sure you're not cheating anybody, but
you don't need a בית דין beis din to approve
it. So that seems like a very powerful argument. אמר ליה אביי,
Amar lei Abaye, so Abaye responded: ולאו איתמר עלה, v'lav itmar alah,
one minute was said about this, אמר רב יוסף בר מניומי אמר
רב נחמן אלמנה אינה צריכה בית דין של מומחין. amar Rav Yosef
bar Minyumi amar Rav Nachman almanah einah tzrichah beis din shel mumchin.
She doesn't need a בית דין beis din, of like experts of
like people with סמיכה, smicha, אבל צריכה בית דין של הדיוטות, aval
tzrichah beis din shel hedyotos, she needs at least a בית דין
of laypeople. So maybe that's a different level like and well, this
is an interesting question, and when you're making this stipulation to return
an אבדה, aveida, do you need a בית דין של מומחין? beis
din shel mumchin? You know, it's pretty hard to find a בית
דין של מומחין beis din shel mumchin if you're trying to return
an אבדה. aveida. But anyway, but it's basically saying, the גמרא Gemara's
is pushing back and saying, no, even if, you know, we are
not basically obligating somebody in something they're not yet obligated in, any
type of a thing that's like unilateral and the other side isn't
represented, you know, needs a, you know, needs somebody to represent their
interests even if it is not like creating a new obligation like
it is in this case of the אבדה. aveida. Yes. I've never
seen the term בית דין של הדיוטות beis din shel hedyotos before.
Really? Oh, totally appears. In the גמרא? Gemara Yeah, all the time.
When I mean, whenever the גמרא Gemara discusses בית דין, it often
looks at versus מומחין mumchin or הדיוטות. hedyotos. Alright, let's take a
look now, next משנה. Mishna Okay, similar to a previous משנה Mishna.
yesterday where it would describe like for the animal wandering, what's the
scenario that you think an animal is an אבדה aveida or not,
like sort of like expanding from the פסוקים. psukim. We're going to
start with that and then we're going to get also to an
interesting exceptions. מצא ברפת אין חייב בה. matza b'refes ein chayav bah.
If you find it in the barn, you don't have to return
it. That's good to know. He has no barn. That's what the
גמרא gemara is going to discuss that. ברשות הרבים חייב בה. birshus
harabim chayav bah. In the public domain, then you are חייב. chayav.
Again, some things where there's more context that we need here. ואם
הייתה בבית הקברות, v'im haysa b'veis hakevaros, now getting to the more
important point, you know, the one we have which which is in
one of the... we've... and this is the third of the three
exceptions in the ברייתא. Braisa. First we had the exception about it's
not for your dignity, then we had the exception that it's, you
know, it's you have to protect your... well, in the ברייתא Braisa
was the first, but the third that we're seeing in the משנה.
Mishna. Then it was that you have to protect your own financial
interests first and the third is you don't violate a prohibition to
return it. Okay. ואם הייתה בבית הקברות, v'im haysa b'veis hakevaros, if
it's in a cemetery and you're a כהן, kohein, לא יטמא לה,
lo yitama lah, don't become טמא tamei in the process of returning
it. אם אמר לו אביו, im amar lo aviv, now if your
father says: היטמא, hitama, so now not only do you have a
מצוה mitzvah of השבת אבדה, hashavas aveida, but you have a מצוה
mitzvah to respect your father, to listen to your father, he said
become... or maybe this isn't even about an אבדה, aveida, just סתם
stam your father tells you, you're a כהן kohein and your father's
telling you become... go... become טמא. tamei. או שאמר לו אל תחזיר,
o she'amar lo al tachazir, or your father tells you don't return
an אבדה. aveida. So basically now you have a מצוה mitzvah of
listening to your father against a divine command. In those cases, לא
ישמע לו, lo yishma lo, don't listen to your father. Now, well,
this... so we'll see about this in the גמרא. gemara Now we
shift completely, shift gears, this should be a separate משנה. Mishna Now
we are moving on from אבדה aveida to the מצוה mitzvah of
פריקה וטעינה prika u'teina which we discussed in passing before and now
we're going to focus on it. פרק וטען פרק וטען. parek v'ta'an
parek v'ta'an. So it's funny the משנה Mishna just jumps straight into
פריקה וטעינה, prika u'teina, does not describe what your obligation is in
those cases, starts by talking about the fact about like that you
have to do it, you know, multiple times. If you unloaded and
reloaded, unloaded and reloaded and the owner and the animal still struggling
and collapsed, אפילו ארבעה וחמישה פעמים חייב, afilu arba'ah v'chamisha pe'amim chayav,
even four and five times you have to keep on doing it.
Don't say I've already done it, the guy's now on his own.
שנאמר עזוב תעזוב, shene'emar azov ta'azov, you shall surely help. Yes, as
I said differently. I understood עזוב azov is many times. No, no,
no, the משנה Mishna yesterday by השב תשיבם hasheiv teshivem was exactly
like this, that the double language suggested... the משנה Mishna says the
double language means multiple times. רבא Rava said, not the ברייתא, Braisa,
רבא Rava claimed no, the first word means many times and the
second word is to expand the scope. Okay, I understand, I understand,
I understand. But anyway, in the משנה Mishna, the double language is
what's telling you multiple times. Anyway, we're now in the world of
פריקה וטעינה. prika u'teina. הלך וישב לו, halach v'yashav lo, now let's
say the owner goes and sits down and says: הואיל ועליך מצוה,
ho'il v'alecha mitzvah,
since you've got a מצוה mitzvah to unload and reload my animal,
אם רצונך
לפרוק, im rtzoncha lifrok, go ahead, do it, be my guest and
I'm going to go... I'll go... I'll go to the Starbucks, I'll
come back, let me know when you're done, okay? In that case,
פטור, patur, you are exempt. שנאמר, shene'emar, as the verse says: עמו,
imo, you shall do it with him. If he's able-bodied and present
and able to help you and he refuses to, then you're not
obligated. Okay. אם היה זקן, im hayah zaken, now let's say he's
there but he's not able, So in that case, פטור *patur*. You
are exempt. שנאמר *shenemar*, the verse says עמו imo, *imo*. You shall
do it with him. If he's able-bodied and present and able to
help you and he refuses to, then you're not obligated. Okay? אם
היה זקן *im hayah zaken*, now let's say he's there but he's
not able, he's elderly, או חולה *o choleh*, then חייב chayav, *chayav*,
then you have to help him even if, do it even if
he's not able. Okay, you, but if he's able and refuses then
you're exempt. מצוה מן התורה לפרוק אבל לא לטעון mitzvah min haTorah
lifrok aval lo liton. *mitzvah min ha-Torah lifrok aval lo litoan*. The
real מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* in the תורה Torah, *Torah* is to unload
the animal, not to reload it. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
going to question that. How can you say that? The תורה Torah
*Torah* says that you're supposed to reload it. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara's* going to say, well, we'll see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says. I won't ruin the surprise. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon אומר אף
לטעון *Rabbi Shimon omer af litoan*. No, there's even a מצוה mitzvah.
*mitzvah* to reload it. רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili אומר *Rabbi
Yosi ha-Glili omer*, רבי Rabbi יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yosi ha-Glili* says, אם
היה עליו יתר על משאו אין זקוק לו *im hayah alav yeter
al masao ein zakuk lo*. If the animal, if the owner was
negligent and overloaded the animal, so now it is, you know, the
burden is too much for the animal, you don't have any responsibility.
It's his own negligence. שנאמר *shenemar*, תחת משאו *tachat masao*, struggling under
his burden, משאו שיכול לעמוד בו masa'o sheyachol la'amod bo, *masao she-yachol
la-amod bo* means a burden that he could normally manage, not something
that is a disproportionate burden. So of course the question here, which
is going to be the great opportunity for the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
is to say that's all very nice that the owner is being
negligent and maybe you shouldn't be responsible for the owner's property, but
what about the poor suffering animal? Which is going to get us
to the question of whether this מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* of פריקה Perika
וטעינה *perika u-teina* is about, is all, is fully about or at
least partially about the suffering of the animal. Yedidya had a question?
Yeah, it's not clear from this last line whether they're talking about
loading or unloading. Yeah, but it would mean even unloading. Okay. Yeah,
so that's kind of saying, meaning the animal's suffering... Right, so that
was... So that's what we're going to see. Whether this is about
property or about the suffering of the animal. At this point the
owner's not around? Either way. Well, if the owner's around, isn't he
responsible that he overloaded
the animal? Yeah, but this would be presumably either way. אמר רבא
Amar Rava. *Amar Rava*, רבא *Rava* said because he was responsible for
initially overloading it, so you don't have... right. but even if... but
whatever. he overloaded it at the home. so it doesn't matter if
he's physically present with the animal. He's negligent to begin with. So
he's not responsible. You're not responsible, right. Okay. אמר רבא *Amar Rava*.
רפת שאמרו *refet she-ameru* אינה מטעה ואינה משמרת *einah mateh v-einah meshameret*.
The barn that we're talking about is one that's not sort of
misleading the animal, but it's not protected either. What does it mean
misleading? Somehow encouraging the animal to run away. What would be a
barn that would be encouraging the animal to run away? So fire,
that's exactly what I thought, a fire. But actually others say basically
means like there are wide open doors all around, okay, or something
like that. And on the other hand, it's not well protected. אינה
מטעה *einah mateh*, how do I know that it's not misleading the
animal? שכיוון דתני אינו חייב chayav בה *she-keivan d-tani eino chayav bah*,
you're not responsible
to return it, okay, so because
if it were, if it were something that the animal was likely
to wander out, like you know the owner left the gate wide
open by accident or something, we'll have to assume סתם stam *stam*
אבידה מדעת aveidah mida'at, *aveidah mi-daat*. Okay, he wasn't being irresponsible but
he forgot and accidentally left the gate open and it's likely for
the animal to wander out, then you are obligated. But again, that's
an interesting case, notice, because that's also a case of אבידה aveida,
*aveidah* on the owner's property, right? It's still there. It's sort of
like protecting the land from being destroyed. You're protecting against
loss. The animal is there and if you don't do something, the
animal is going to wander out and get lost. Do you have
an obligation to close the gate? Right? That would be the question.
You walk by, there's a gate open, the horses are there, in
another two minutes they're going to realize the gate is open and
they're all going to run out of the gate. Okay, so then
you have an obligation to close the gate. Okay, so that's how
you know, since it says you're not obligated, you know that it's
not sort of misleading the animals and encouraging them to leave. Okay.
ואינה משמרת *v-einah meshameret*, on the other hand you have to say
that it's not well protected, it's not like the animals are in
their normal circumstance of being in a closed-in barn. מדאיצטריך למתני אינו
חייב chayav, בה *mi-d-itztrich le-matni eino chayav bah*, since it had to
tell me I don't have an obligation... I mean if an animal's
in a barn, then of course I don't have an obligation. דאי
סלקא דעתך משמרת *de-i salka dach-tach meshameret*, if I think that it
was totally protected, השתא מצאה בחוץ *hashta matza'ah ba-chutz*, if you found
the animal wandering outside, מעיילי ליה *m'aylei leh*, what do you do?
You put it back into the barn, okay, and you don't even
have to tell the owner. So that's what it means to protect
the animal and return it is have it in the barn. So
if that's true, מצאה בפנים מיבעיא *matza'ah bi-fnim mibaya*?
So if I found it in the barn, you have to tell
me I don't have to do anything with it? Of course, that's
what, of course it's not an אבידה aveida. *aveidah*. אלא שמע מינה
אינה משמרת *ella shema mina einah meshameret*, שמע מינה *shema mina*. It
means it's not totally protected, okay? So which is interesting, what's exactly
the limit, right? So when is it my responsibility? So if it
seems like it's likely that the animal's going to run out, I
should close the gate, I do. If it's like, okay, it's not
totally protected, but it'll only escape under some rare circumstance, then that's
not my
responsibility. Yes, there is a breach in the gate, you know, if
it gets upset or I don't know, somehow agitated, maybe it'll find
the breach and run out, but that's not the circumstances right now.
So some type of a possible
future event is not my responsibility. Some type of an anticipated future
event is my responsibility. Okay, so drawing the line between possible and
anticipated. might not always be clear, but that at least explains what
the משנה Mishna, is doing. Okay, moving on. מצא ברפת אינו חייב,
Matza berefet eino chayav,
back into that case if it's in the barn you're not obligated.
אמר יצחק, Amar Yitzchak, והוא שעומדת תוך לתחום, vehu she'omedet toch letchum,
when is that that you're not required? If it is inside the
city boundaries, okay? But if it's outside the city boundaries, and again
we're dealing with a case where it's a little unprotected, then the
combination of the two, a little unprotected plus outside of the town
and the owner might not see it, and if it wanders off
it'll more likely get lost and not be able to be retrieved,
then you would be required. Okay, so it's an interesting constellation of
issues. מכלל דברשות הרבים, Michlal de'bireshut harabim, which would mean that if
it's wandering in the public domain, אפילו בתוך התחום, afilu betoch hatchum,
even if it's within city boundaries, נמי חייב, nami chayav, okay, you're
also obligated. So this rate of reading the ברייתא braita heightens the
level of
obligation, okay? That if it's in a public domain, even in the
city boundaries you're חייב, chayav and if it's in a
barn, then you're only not חייב chayav. when it's, let me see
if I read that right... והוא שעומדת... vehu she'omedet... No. Yeah.
When it's in a public domain even in the city boundaries you're
חייב, chayav. and when it's in a barn out of the city
boundaries you're also חייב chayav if it's a little bit not protected.
Any one of those two factors is enough to make you חייב.
Either רשות הרבים reshut harabim or outside of the city תחום. tchum.
Again, assuming that the barn is a little not protected. Okay, that's
one way of reading it. איכא דמתני לה אסיפא, Ika dematni lah
aseifa, some say this on the end of the משנה, mishnah, and
lower your level of responsibility. ברשות הרבים חייב, Bireshut harabim chayav,
you're obligated if it's in the public domain. אמר יצחק, Amar Yitzchak,
והוא שעומדת חוץ לתחום, vehu she'omedet chutz letchum, but only two, two
things make you חייב. Both it's wandering in the public domain and
it's outside of the city boundaries. Okay? אבל מכלל דברפת, Aval michlal
de'berefet, but if you have either one of those, you're exempt. If
it's in a barn, אפילו עומדת חוץ לתחום, afilu omedet chutz letchum,
even if it's outside of the town boundaries, נמי אינו חייב, nami
eino chayav, you're not obligated. Okay? So very interesting, there's, it's not
just a trivial question of where to read the משנה, right? It's
a real question about what is, what are the circumstances, right? What
are the that you are, you know, how much concern, what's the
level of concern that makes you obligated? Yes. So a רשות הרבים
reshut harabim that is outside of the תחום, tchum, I was wondering
about that. No, but I assume it means it's sort of like
an interstate, you know what I mean? You have a רשות הרבים
reshut harabim that is not going to be the same רשות הרבים
reshut harabim as we talk about with, really? Could be a bigger
one. It could be one that's between cities. Think about where all
the caravans go. No, I'm serious. Okay, so you certainly could have,
you know, big streets that are not in a, in your town's
תחום. tchum. Not in ancient times, we have no evidence of big
roads like that, except for a few Roman roads. Really? How about
even in the תורה, Torah דרך המלך נלך, derech hamelech neilech, they
actually say there was the king's highway. That wasn't just a term.
But there was, it was. It wasn't Interstate 95. Okay, so it
wasn't paved. But what, all right, anyway. All right, I don't know
but, but anyway, I assume we're talking about some big road that
connects towns. Okay. בבית הקברות לא יטמא לה. Beveit hakevarot lo yitama
lah. Now we get into these interesting other exceptions. Don't, don't become
טמא tamei to return an אבידה. aveida תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. מניין
שאם אמר לו אביו, Minayin she'im amar lo aviv, so we're actually
going to completely skip over the idea, the first part of it,
which is that the מצוה mitzvah of returning an אבידה aveida doesn't
override becoming טמא. tamei. We discussed that earlier. First of all, an
עשה aseh cannot override a לא תעשה lo ta'aseh and an עשה.
aseh. There's a לא תעשה lo ta'aseh and עשה aseh of a
כהן kohen becoming טמא. tamei. לנפש לא יטמא Lenefesh lo yitama and
קדושים תהיו. kedoshim tihyu. Also the גמרא Gemara at that time mentioned,
and I want to bring that up here, that a מצוה mitzvah
of ממון mamon doesn't override this more like ritual מצוה. mitzvah And
people were a little bit offended by that because they made it
sound like
monetary issues are less important than ritual ones? Okay, and I said
no, no, no, it just means that like, you know, money can
always somehow be replaced in a way that, you know, it's not
like it's more or less in terms of which overrides which, it's
not really a question of importance. So actually it's going to be
an opportunity to look at that right now. Because the גמרא's skipping
over the becoming טמא tamei to return an אבידה aveida and going
straight to listening to your father. So let's take a look. Okay.
מניין שאם אמר לו אביו, Minayin she'im amar lo aviv, how do
you know if your father says to you, הטמא, hitama, become טמא,
tamei, just stam, says yeah, I know you're a כהן kohen my
son, but I want you to go to the בית הקברות. beit
hakevarot. Okay? Or, you know, go whatever, go visit your aunt's grave
even though you're not allowed as a כהן. kohen. או שאמר לו
אל תחזיר, O she'amar lo al tachzir, or he tells you don't
return an אבידה, aveida. שלא ישמע לו, shelo yishma lo, how do
I know you shouldn't listen to your father or mother? שנאמר איש
אמו ואביו תיראו ואת שבתותי תשמורו, Shene'emar ish imo ve'aviv tira'u ve'et
shabtotai tishmoru,
fear your mother and father and observe my Sabbaths. אני השם, Ani
Hashem, I am God. כולכם חייבין בכבודי. Kulchem chayavin bichvodi.
It means all of you at the end of the day have
to answer to me. Yes, fear your, respect your parents, but at
the end of the day also keep my Sabbaths, I'm God, I'm
the one here that in the end you're all answerable to. So
don't listen to them when they tell you to violate one of
my commands. Now this is interesting because even if he tells you
don't return an אבידה. aveida So based on the calculus we said
the other day, you could say, well, מצוה mitzvah of respect my
father or honor my father, and an אבידה aveida. is just a
money issue. So maybe respecting my father should trump a monetary obligation,
right? And here we say no, it doesn't, actually, it's
not. money, monetary obligations pale compared to ritual obligations or something like
that. You know, here your father did not have a right to
tell you to do that, and that's not included in honoring of
your father, and therefore you have to return the אבידה aveida, and
you don't listen to your father. Now another of course there you
could say it's a little different. It's not because it doesn't trump,
it's because the scope of listening to your father doesn't include, you
know, like from the very outset, your obligations of honor don't extend
to cases where your father is, you know, is telling you to
violate a religious obligation. Okay, so it's a little different there. It
might not be which trumps which, but whether that fundamentally you're obligated
to respect in those cases. Anyway, the other important point to mention
here is why is this included in honoring or fearing your father?
The גמרא normally says, you know, that honoring a parent is means
taking care of their needs, feeding them, dressing them, you know, accompanying
them to doctor's appointments and so on. Fear or awe of parents
is, you know, not to contradict them, not to disrespect them, you
know, speak to them in a certain way, act in public with,
you know, towards them in a certain way. So how is not
returning an אבידה aveida incorporated in this? So, this leads to an
important discussion in the ראשונים Rishonim and פוסקים Poskim whether is obeying
your parents included in the מצוה mitzvah of honoring your parents, of
כיבוד אב ואם. Kibbud Av v'Em. Of course, don't tell your kids
this because it's the only way we sometimes get some leverage. What
do you mean? You have to listen to me! There's a מצוה
mitzvah of honoring your parents! But actually, from a halakhic
perspective, a lot of פוסקים Poskim feel that maybe that's only דרבנן.
d'rabbanan. Like, you know, yes, you're not supposed to contradict your parents,
meaning don't not listen to them in a disrespectful way, in a
way that shows that you reject their role and their
authority. But if you sort of, but if you sort of, you
know, you say, yes, I respect what you say and whatever, but
at the end of the day, I have to make my own
decisions in my life, you know, and so on. And maybe it's
a different whether you're talking about a kid or an adult or
whatever. You know, there's a way in which you just, you know,
that that not listening is not the same as disrespecting. Okay, or
not obeying is certainly maybe not listening is not the same, is
the same, but not obeying is not the same as disrespecting. So
the question then becomes, so if that's true, how of course I
don't have to listen to my father tells me don't return the
אבידה. aveida He, that's not even included in the normal מצוה mitzvah.
of כיבוד אב ואם ויראה. Kibbud Av v'Em v'Yira. There's no מצוה
mitzvah to listen to everything my father says. So a lot of
ראשונים Rishonim say, well, what we're talking about is he's saying, no,
I don't want you to return that אבידה aveida because I want
you to be here taking care of me. Don't go running around
returning that אבידה. aveida. I need you here, I need you here,
you know, helping me in the house. I need you here preparing
my meals. Okay, so that would be a מצוה mitzvah, of כיבוד
אב ואם. Kibbud Av v'Em. So he's not telling you just for
the sake of violating God's will. He says, no, I want you
to prioritize taking care of my needs over this מצוה mitzvah of
השבת אבידה. hashavat aveida. Okay, or let's say he says, look, I
lost an object and it's in the cemetery, or, you know, something
that I want is in the cemetery and I want you to
go retrieve it and it's a way of taking care of my
needs, okay, because there's something that I need from you to to
help me with my needs that I need you to go into
the cemetery. So that makes it more reasonable. He's not סתם just
saying, don't listen to God. He's saying, do this because this is
what I need to take care of my needs. And nevertheless, because
it leads to a
violation, you know, you're exempt, which makes it particularly
shocking if you think about if it is a scenario that he
says I need you at home cooking for me, don't go returning
an אבידה, aveida that you don't listen to him. Which is interesting,
because when I need to, when I need to not return an
אבידה aveida, because it's beneath my dignity, I don't return it. When
I need to not return an אבידה aveidah, because I'm going to
lose out too much money, I don't return it. So it would
be reasonable to think when I need to not return an אבידה
because my father needs me at home, I should not return it.
Right? So that actually is quite interesting, you know, and it also
gets to the question that Mike was asking earlier. Let's say I,
let's say my employer needs me to keep still be working, somebody
else's needs, would that override my obligation? So it becomes very interesting
when we try to imagine what is the scenario here that the
father is saying don't return the אבידה. Okay, so there's a lot
of really interesting discussions here about כיבוד אב ואם. Kibbud Av v'Em.
So now the גמרא continues. טעמא דכתב רחמנא, Ta'ama d'katav Rachmana, the
reason is that the Torah said את שבתותי תשמורו. et shabbotai tishmoru.
הלאו הכי, Halav hachi, because the פסוק pasuk told us don't listen
to your father when it means violating the מצוה. mitzvah הלאו הכי,
Halav hachi, if it wasn't for this, I would think ציית ליה,
tsayeit leih, listen to your father. ואמאי, V'amai, האי עשה ולא תעשה
ועשה? hai aseh v'lo ta'aseh v'aseh? Honoring your parents is a מצות
עשה. mitzvot aseh. Not the, you know, not returning an אבידה or
becoming טמא tamei is a לא תעשה lo ta'aseh and an עשה.
aseh. הלא תעשה Ha'lo ta'aseh is
לנפש לא יטמא l'nefesh lo yitama or and קדושים תהיו. Kedoshim Tihyu.
That's a לא תעשה lo ta'aseh and עשה aseh by becoming טמא
tamei if you're a כהן. kohen. And the אבידה, the לא תעשה
lo ta'aseh is לא תוכל להתעלם lo tuchal l'hitalem and והשבותו לו.
v'hashivoto lo. So of course the positive מצוה mitzvah of your parents
would not override these other מצוות. mitzvot. Okay? והאי עשה ולא תעשה
ודחי לא תעשה ועשה, v'hai aseh v'lo ta'aseh v'dechi lo ta'aseh v'aseh,
and it
should not override. And notice what that also means is that even
the ritual obligation, I don't want to say the ritual, but the
obligation... Nevertheless you needed the פסוק. pasuk. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka deitach
amina, I would have thought והוקש כיבוד אב ואם לכיבוד המקום, v'hukash
kivud av va'em l'kivud hamakom, since honoring parents is compared to honoring
God, שנאמר כבד את אביך ואת אמך, shene'emar kabeid et avicha v'et
imecha, שנאמר כבד את ה' מהונך, shene'emar kabeid et Hashem meihonecha, honor
your mother and father and also it says
honor God from your wealth, הלכך לציית ליה, hilkach l'tzayes lei,
therefore maybe that constitutes honoring God and maybe that would trump other
מצוות mitzvot of, you know, of the Torah. קא משמע לן דלא
לשמע ליה, ka mashma lan d'lo lishmah lei, so it tells you
no, ultimately honoring God is not listening to them is more that
you're all paying attention to the מצוות mitzvot I gave that apply
to all of you, okay, and not everything your father said is
like God has just now told it to you and it overrides
other things. Alright, מצוה, mitzvah? so that was, like I said, there's
a lot there in terms of כיבוד אב ואם kivud av va'em
and also in terms of these issues we discussed about what happens
if returning an אבידה, I forgo it, not to save myself loss
but to be available to my employer, to be available to my
father and so on. Okay, now, now we completely shift gears to
פרק אלו מציאות. perek eilu metziot. מצוה mitzvah מן התורה לפרוק אבל
לא לטעון. There's a מצוה mitzvah in the Torah to unload but
not to reload. מאי אבל לא לטעון? mai aval lo liton? What
does it mean there's no מצוה mitzvah to reload? אילימא אבל לא
לטעון כלל, ilima aval lo liton klal, there's no מצוה mitzvah to
reload the animal, מאי שנא פריקה דכתיב עזוב תעזוב? mai shna prika
d'chtiv azov ta'azov? Why
unloading it says you shall certainly help the person עמו, with him?
טעינה נמי הכתיב הקם תקים עמו? teina nami hachtiv hakem takim imo?
If the animal's fallen down, you should stand the animal back up,
so standing it back up presumably means with reloading it, okay, so
they're both in the Torah, what do you mean one's not a
מצוה? mitzvah אלא, no, מצוה מן התורה לפרוק בחינם. mitzvah min haTorah
lifrok b'chinam. No, unloading you do for free because that involves as
we're gonna see suffering of an animal and loss of property, so
of course you do it for free, putting, bracketing the question about
like if you have to be, you know, שכר בטלה. schar batala.
ולא לטעון בחינם v'lo liton b'chinam but you have no obligation to
reload for free אלא בשכר ela b'schar but but you can accept
payment because it's quite interesting, right? Why am I obligated to help
you reload your animal? Like here's a question, like forget this, here
I am, I'm walking down the street and I see somebody putting
their luggage in their car. Okay, do I have a מצוה mitzvah
to stop, I mean the right thing to do of course is
to say hey, do you need help, right? But is there a
מצוה mitzvah for me to stop and to help the guy put
the luggage in his car? I mean you know, am I violating
something if I don't do that? We would normally call that I
don't know גמילות חסד gemilut chesed or something, you know, but so
why should there be a מצוה to load up his animal? I've
unloaded it, we've just said a minute ago that it's not too
heavy of a load, if it's too heavy of a load that's
a different conversation, right? So now that the animal's had a chance
to recover, whatever, let the owner take care of now handling it
back. So it's actually quite fascinating that in this scenario, right, I
have an obligation to load. So the גמרא is saying is fine,
it's an obligation, but you can be paid because it's kind of
be harder. If you walk away and he needs help, right, he's
going to have to start calling on, you know, getting on his
phone calling people, whatever, so you're there to help, he clearly needs
help, so provide him with that help, but at the end of
the day, right, it's not like there's going to be a like
I, it's clear that I don't have to stop doing everything I'm
doing and go and help everybody in the world that needs help,
right? Every time I walk by, you know, I go door to
door and see people that need help bringing their groceries home and
people that need help loading up their car, I'm never going to
get home, right? So so it's an interesting case that yes he
needs help but it's not like there's a loss of property going
on here, so help him, but at least you can go ahead
and get paid for that. So the interesting question would be let's
say it wasn't in this scenario, right, let's say you walked by
the guy and his animal had not collapsed, you know, and he
was just, or it had collapsed and he had stood it up
by himself and he was in the process of loading it up,
and you came while he was in the middle of loading it
up. Do you have a מצוה to load it up, or is
your מצוה to load it up only if you encountered it when
the animal had been, you know, had already collapsed and so on?
Because again, normally I don't have to stop, I mean I do
often stop and ask people do you need help with this or
whatever, but that's not, you know, strictly obligated to stop and help
everybody that's in the middle of, you know, doing their business, yes.
Wasn't רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon the רבי who said we were not
supposed to be working anyway, we were supposed to be studying Torah
all the time? Would he say that you are required to stop
studying Torah to do these things? Well that's another interesting question about
stopping Torah to do these things, which is actually discussed, yes. Also
to awkward situation so you walk up to a person and say
like if you pay me I'll help you and if not I'm
not going to help you. Yeah, well I mean there's other ways
to say it, you'd say like you know do you need any
help and he says yes and say I'd be happy to help
but you know but just I just need to like you know
I would just need to get paid because I'm going to be
missing from my job. Would you still like, there's ways you can
frame it, you know, you don't start by saying hey buddy do
you want to pay me and I'll help you, you know, you
but anyway but yeah, okay and okay anyway but it is quite
fascinating that there is this מצוה and because of that the גמרא
says you do have a right. right to be paid and like
I'm saying you have to ask yourself like what are the scenarios
that I have the מצוה to load the load to load up.
Okay, now the גמרא says like this: רב הונא אומר אף טעינה
בחינם. Rav Huna omer af te'inah bechinnam. You should even load it
up for free. תנינא להא דתנו רבנן, Tanina leha detanu rabbanan, we
taught our משנה, we taught in a ברייתא braita what we teach
in a ברייתא: braita: פריקה בחינם טעינה בשכר. Perika bechinnam te'inah besachar.
Unloading is for free, loading up you can get paid. רב הונא
אומר זו וזו בחינם, Rav Huna omer zu vezu bechinnam, both are
for free. מאי טעמא דרבנן? Mai ta'ama derabbanan? What's the reason of
the Rabbis? דאי סלקא דעתך כרבי שמעון, De'isalka deitach k'Rabbi Shimon, if
you believe like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that it was both for
free, לכתוב רחמנא טעינה ולא בעי פריקה. Lichtov Rachamana te'inah velo ba'ei
perika. Let the תורה Torah just say load and don't say you
have to unload. ואנא אמינא, Va'ana amina, and I would say: ומה
טעינה דלית בה צער בעלי חיים, uma te'inah deleis bah tza'ar ba'alei
chayim, when you're unloading the animal is not suffering, ולכא חסרון כיס,
veleika chisron kis, and the animal is not about to die. Okay,
maybe again the owner will lose some time because he has to,
you know, spend time finding people to help him or whatever, but
it's not the same immediate loss of property. And if that you're
חייב and you're obligated to reload, so פריקה דאית בה צער בעלי
חיים וחסרון כיס, perika de'is bah tza'ar ba'alei chayim vechisron kis, unloading
where the animal is suffering and there's an immediate loss of property,
לא כל שכן, lo kol sheken, how much certainly you would have
to? אלא מאי הלכתא כתבה רחמנא? Ela mai hilcheta katvah Rachamana? So
why does the תורה Torah after it said you have to load,
in addition to saying to load, it said you have to unload?
למימרא לך פריקה בחינם טעינה בשכר. Lemeimra lach perika bechinnam te'inah besachar.
פריקה has to be for unloading for free, loading for you can
be paid. רבי שמעון מאי טעמא? Rabbi Shimon mai ta'ama?
Why would רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, say the תורה Torah had to
say it twice? Had to say both, just say unloading and I
could figure out loading, just say loading and I could figure out
unloading. משום דלא מסיימי קראי, Mishum dela mesaymi kra'ei, because the פסוקים
psukim are not clear. The פסוקים psukim say הקם תקים, hakem takim,
עזב תעזב. azov ta'azov. It's not so explicit if that means loading
or unloading. So if it only had said one, I would have
said it meant unloading. It had to say it twice so I
could figure out that one means unloading and one means reloading. But
at the end of the day, they're equal level of obligation. So
the גמרא says: ורבנן אמאי לא מסיימי? Verabbanan amai lo mesaymi? The
Rabbis would say back: What do you mean the פסוקים psukim aren't
clear? הכא כתיב רובץ תחת משאו. Hacha ketiv rovetz tachat masa'o. Here
it says
the animal is like crouching under its burden, so it's clear what's
being addressed is the need to unload it. והתם כתיב, Vehatam ketiv,
and in the other verse it says: נפלים בדרך, nefelim baderech, that
they've fallen down,
which means that the obligation is to reload it. Okay, and not
only that, what does the plural of נפלים nefelim mean? דמי רמא
אינהו וטעונא באורחא. Derama inhu vete'una be'orcha.
The animal has collapsed and the load is spilled on the street.
So if the animal's collapsed and the load is spilled on the
street, there's nothing about unloading the animal that has to get done.
The only thing left to do now is stand the animal up
and reload it. So in one it's clear we're talking about unloading
and in the other it's clear we're talking about reloading. So the
גמרא says: רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon רבי שמעון would say back to
you: No, נפלים בדרך nefelim baderech means אינהו וטעונא עלייהו ממש. inhu
vete'una aleihu mamash. No, no, no, it means the animal with its
load that's still on its back has tipped over. So if the
animal's got its load bound to it and it's tipped over, so
what, how do you get the animal up? What's the first thing
you have to do in order to get the animal up? Unload
it. So even if the animal has fallen over, the פסוק pasuk
could be talking about unloading and not necessarily about reloading. So if
you just had one פסוק, pasuk, you would have said it's only
about unloading and therefore we needed two to tell you unloading and
reloading, but they're actually the same level of obligation. Okay, אמר רבא.
Now we get to the classic, one of the classic discussions in
the גמרא about צער בעלי חיים. tza'ar ba'alei chayim. מדברי שניהם נלמד:
Midevrei sheneihem nilmad: From what both of them say we can infer
that צער בעלי חיים דאורייתא, tza'ar ba'alei chayim de'oraita, that there is
a תורה Torah principle to be concerned about animal suffering. Okay, now
sometimes when we say צער בעלי חיים דאורייתא, tza'ar ba'alei chayim de'oraita,
we mean that there is an independent obligation in the תורה Torah
to alleviate or not induce animal
suffering. Okay, nowhere here are we saying that I have a generic
obligation if I see some animal suffering to alleviate it. What we're
saying here is—is I'm not saying we don't, elsewhere the גמרא does
say צער בעלי חיים דאורייתא tza'ar ba'alei chayim de'oraita means I have
a general obligation. But here what we're saying is that it's a
תורה Torah value, and and we can infer that it's a תורה
Torah value because it plays out in terms of how we understand
the relative importance of unloading versus reloading. And that now since we've
said unloading is more important, we're basically acknowledging that the תורה Torah
is concerned about animal suffering and therefore that gives more weight to
the obligation of unloading than to reloading. So that doesn't necessarily translate
into a generic obligation regarding צער בעלי חיים, tza'ar ba'alei chayim, but
it means it's clearly a תורה value that factors in here to
your obligations. So let's take a look at this. ואפילו רבנן: Ve'afilu
Rabbanan: So number one, the Rabbis who say there's a higher obligation
to unload, clearly it's because צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim is
a factor. And even רבי שמעון לא קאמר אלא משום דלא מסיימי
קראי. Rabbi Shimon lo ka'amar ela mishum dela mesaymi kra'ei. The only
reason we're saying he rejects the Rabbis is because the פסוקים psukim
are not explicit, you know, which is unloading, which is reloading. אבל
מסיימי קראי, Aval mesaymi kra'ei, if they were explicit, דרשינן קל וחומר.
darshinan kal vachomer. He basically agrees to the Rabbis' logic. weighty obligation
than reloading. Okay, משום מאי? mishum mai? What is that about? לאו
משום צער בעלי חיים? lav mishum tza'ar ba'alei chayim? Is it not
because of צער בעלי חיים? tza'ar ba'alei chayim? It must be because
of צער בעלי חיים
דאורייתא tza'ar ba'alei chayim d'oraisa that we care about the suffering of
animals, and therefore both the Rabbis and Rabbi Shimon agree in principle
that unloading is a weightier obligation. It must be because of צער
בעלי חיים. tza'ar ba'alei chayim. A weightier obligation, I didn't- I didn't
even think about that. Okay. The Gemara says no. דילמא, dilma, the
Gemara says not necessarily. דילמא משום דאיכא חסרון כיס, dilma mishum de'ika
chisron kis,
no, maybe the difference is not that the animal is suffering, but
that the animal might collapse and die or be injured, meaning maybe
we don't care about the animal at all, we just care about
the owner losing a good usable donkey. Okay, so it's not about
the donkey suffering, it's about the owner losing a donkey, okay, and
that's the difference. והכי קאמר, vehachi ka'amar,
and that's why
reloading is less of an obligation than unloading. ומה טעינה דלית בה
חסרון כיס חייב, uma te'ina deleis bah chisron kis chayav,
reloading, there's no loss of the animal, the animal's fine now, okay,
and nevertheless you're obligated to reload. פריקה דאית בה חסרון כיס, prika
de'is bah chisron kis, unloading, where there is a loss of money,
that the animal might actually collapse and die, לא כל שכן, lo
kol sheken, how much more so? So yes, unloading is a greater
obligation, but not necessarily because of suffering, but because the animal might
die and that'll be a loss to the owner. Okay, so the
Gemara says one minute. וטעינה אין בה חסרון כיס? ute'ina ein bah
chisron kis? You can't say that the only difference is loss. Who
says that there's no loss with the reloading case? וטעינה אין בה
חסרון כיס? ute'ina ein bah chisron kis? Are you telling me that
reloading will never have a case of loss? מי לא עסקינן דאדהכי
והכי בטיל משוקיה? mi lo askinan d'adeihachi vehachi batil mishukei?
Who's to say that by the time it takes him to find
other people to help him reload his animal, he's going to lose
out the market, you know, he's bringing his wares to the market,
if he can't find people to help him, he's going to miss
out all those opportunities? So clearly there could be cases of loss
by reloading as well. So the big difference between unloading and reloading
is not loss, the big difference is צער בעלי חיים. tza'ar ba'alei
chayim. אינמי, inami, or forget that he'll miss the market, אתו גנבי
ושקלי כל מה דאיכא בהדיה, asu ganvei veshakli kol mah de'ika bahadeih,
he's there in the middle of the road and he's stuck, you
know, some bandits are going to come in and strip him clean.
Okay, so there's actually a risk to his property and his life
in that
case. So the real difference of these cases is not loss, there's
likely loss in both scenarios, the real difference is צער בעלי חיים.
tza'ar ba'alei chayim. It is different, one is an immediate loss and
the one is a possible future loss, I understand. Loss to different
people, one is the loss of the animal to the owner of
the animal and the other is a loss to the person who's
assisting, and if there's an agreement-
no, no, no, we're both talking about losses to the owner. Either
the owner will lose his animal because it will collapse under the
burden and die, or the owner will lose his opportunity to bring
the wares to market, or the owner will be stuck by the
wayside and people will come and steal the animal and the wares.
It's all loss to the owner of the animal. So the owner
should kill the animal, put him out of- no, you should help
him reload the animal so he can get moving. But the point
is both unloading and reloading save the owner from loss and the
real difference therefore if we're going to say unloading has greater weight
is צער בעלי חיים. tza'ar ba'alei chayim. So the Gemara says תדע,
teda, and let's just read a little bit more here, תדע דצער
בעלי חיים דאורייתא, teda detza'ar ba'alei chayim d'oraisa, you should know that
it's a Torah principle, דקתני סיפא, dekatani seifa, the Mishnah continues in
the end, רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר אם היה עליו יתר על משאו
אין זקוק לו. Rabbi Yossi HaGlili omer im hayah alav yoser al
masa'o ein zakuk lo. So Rabbi Yossi HaGlili clearly does not care
about צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim because he says if it's
overburdened and the owner's to blame, you don't have to help it,
so the owner brought this loss upon itself, which means we only
care about the owner's loss, not about the animal. שנאמר תחת משאו,
shenemar tachat masa'o, under its burden, משאו שיכול לעמוד בו, לאו מכלל,
lav michlal, from that we infer דתנא קמא סבר זקוק לו, detanna
kamma savar zakuk lo, that even if it is overburdened, you have
to help. If it was all about the owner's loss, we would
normally say it's like the Gemara calls אבידה מדעת, aveidah mida'at you
brought it on yourself, it's not my responsibility. So מאי טעמא? mai
ta'ama? לאו משום דצער בעלי חיים דאורייתא? lav mishum detza'ar ba'alei chayim
d'oraisa? Is it not- it must be that you're obligated in that
case, even though the owner was to blame, because of the principle
of צער בעלי חיים. tza'ar ba'alei chayim. So Gemara says no, maybe
not, דילמא בתחת משאו פליגי, dilma betachat masa'o pligi, maybe it's just
a technical debate of how to read the פסוק. pasuk. דרבי יוסי
הגלילי סבר דרשינן תחת משאו, deRabbi Yossi HaGlili savar darshinan tachat masa'o,
we read the words to mean משאו הראוי שיכול לעמוד בו, masa'o
haraui sheyachol la'amod bo, a fit burden. ורבנן סברי לא דרשינן תחת
משאו, veRabbanan savri la darshinan tachat masa'o, we don't read it to
mean a fit burden. Of course the funny point is that even
if that's not how you read the פסוקים, psukim, even if you
don't read the פסוקים psukim to be explicitly limiting that case, the
general idea like the Gemara said before that we should treat this
as a type of an אבידה מדעת seems to be like a
compelling logic. But in the end the Gemara says you know what,
maybe the Torah's telling us here not have רחמנות rachmanus on the
animal, maybe the Torah's telling us here, even if the owner brought
it upon himself and overburdened the animal, have רחמנות rachmanus on the
owner, okay, you know, because sometimes that's what people
do. So I'm being an idiot. Okay? Fine. I'm being an idiot.
But if somebody sees me struggling, they should help me anyway, okay?
So, so yes, it's possible that it's a technical debate, and it
certainly seems that רבי יוסי הגלילי is not concerned with suffering of
animals, 'cause he lets the animal suffer and says you walk away.
But the Rabbis, it's not clear. Are they concerned with the animal's
suffering, or are they saying even if the owner was to blame,
you should be helping out the owner anyway, but it's really not
about the animal? So we'll continue with this tomorrow to see this
issue about whether צער בעלי חיים Tzaar Baalei Chayim is a תורה
principle or not. Okay. We want to do a catch-up session tomorrow.